hey folks Bret here I want to talk to
you about a thought that has been
preoccupying me over the last several
months and it's a concern about where
intersectionality is going to lead us
but in order to understand the concern I
have to step back into evolutionary
history there are really two ways in
which cooperation evolves the first one
is very ancient it is based on genetic
relatedness and it's very hard to put a
starting point in it but it literally
goes back billions of years the other
kind of cooperation is based on various
kinds of reciprocity and it is much
newer and much more fragile it really
gets going in human beings after the
invention of farming approximately
10,000 years ago the problem stems from
the fact that when reciprocity based
cooperation breaks down we default to
gene based cooperation now look at that
in the context of intersectionality
which has captured the attention of the
far left intersectionality effectively
argues that people have different kinds
of oppression that they have
historically suffered from based on the
categories that they inhabit so your
race your gender your your sex all carry
degrees of oppression that come from
history and the intersection lists would
like to transfer well-being from those
who have historically been privileged to
those who have historically been
oppressed based essentially on an
accounting scheme how many different
kinds of oppression have you faced and
what are the implications of how those
different kinds of oppression interact
but the problem is that this way of
thinking which is very frequently a
cartoon of reality it does not depict
the way oppression actually functions in
the present lacks nuance but beyond that
in order to function it has to define
an enemy the enemy is effectively a
fiction in this case it is something
called whiteness and the way the enemy
is drawn whiteness is an inherent
characteristic something that can be
read on the skin and what that means is
there's no escaping it so for people who
suffer from whiteness you are simply
going to be on the losing end of the
intersectional juggernaut no matter what
you do if you think about how that is
likely to unfold people who are the
object of ire from the intersection list
are going to be backed against the wall
together who are they going to be well
primarily they're going to be straight
and white and very frequently male what
happens though if you back straight
white males against the wall together
well think about what goes on in the
intersectional side as the intersection
lists take power the coalition that they
have assembled is likely to break down
in other words those who are on the
intersectional side but are not at the
top of it have a lot to lose in the
reordering of things that would come
from a win by the intersection list so
cooperation game theoretically is very
likely to break down amongst the
intersection lists at the same time the
people who they have backed against the
wall together have a second basis for
cooperation and it is much more durable
it is genetic cooperation so the concern
that I have is that the intersection
lists may end up creating the very enemy
they claim they are fighting they're
going to back straight white males
against the wall and speak of the devil
white nationalism will emerge from that
cohort and when it does those people
will feel empowered and they will feel
self-righteous because they have been
accused of things that are frankly a
form of bigotry they have been accused
by bigots of oppressing others and they
have been told that they are not
entitled to well-being no matter how
they individually have
behaved and so what do they have to lose
by cooperating together against the
intersection 'less and essentially
creating the world that the intersection
was claimed already exists now what we
should do about this is not entirely
clear but one thing that must happen is
we must level up our thinking and we
must understand that backing people
against the wall who have a genetic
basis for cooperation is very dangerous
because history tells us that movements
created by such people can be very
destructive and that ultimately they may
turn into a genocidal menace so what is
the outgrowth of all of this
preoccupation that I've had on this
topic I think the answer is fairly clear
the answer is that we must recognize
that the very best things that human
beings are capable of are based on this
more elevated type of cooperation we
have to resist the urge to fall into
this negative kind of tribalism that is
driven on both sides by the
intersectional movement and we must
foster the kind of cooperation that has
spread over the course of recent history
where people increasingly ignore genetic
relatedness and they find other reasons
to get along and to prosper together hey
folks if you like this video click like
subscribe to the channel and if you feel
like supporting the creation of more
content like this head on over to my
patreon page and sign up at whatever
level feels comfortable